<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A particular relation of the raising of the siege of Vienna, and the defeat of the Turkish army on the 12th of September, 1683.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1683</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 7 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 2 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B04917</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P604</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R181489</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">52528870</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 52528870</idno>
            <idno type="VID">178853</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B04917)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 178853)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2773:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A particular relation of the raising of the siege of Vienna, and the defeat of the Turkish army on the 12th of September, 1683.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet (2 p.)   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Re-printed by the heir of Andrew Anderson, printer to his most Excellent Majesty,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1683.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: blurred print with slight loss of text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the National Library of Scotland.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Austro-Turkish War, 1683-1699 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Vienna (Austria) --  History --  Siege, 1683 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Broadsides --  Scotland --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:178853:1"/>
            <head>A Particular Relation of the raiſing of the Siege of <hi>Vienna,</hi> and the Defeat of the Turkiſh Army on the 12th of <hi>September,</hi> 1683.</head>
            <p>YOu have already had ſeveral Relations of the great Victory which the Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate Army obtained against the Turks the twelfth instant, but none ſo exact and particular as that we now give you. The Turks after a Siege of nine Weeks, had reduced this place to that extremity, that it could not have held out <hi>48.</hi> houres longer, for our Proviſions failed, our Gariſon which at first was about <hi>12000.</hi> men, was brought to <hi>6000.</hi> having ſuffered more by ſickneſs than by the Enemy, and the Turks had three Mines ready to ſpring, which would in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibly have blown up the laſt Retrenchment we had made for our ſecurity within the Town, when the Chriſtian Army with the Divine Aſſiſtance happily reliev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed us: Which they would not ſo eaſily have done, had the Grand Viſier ſecured the paſſages of the Wood and other Poſts (which the Christians found difficult enough to paſſe, even though they met with no oppoſition) but either for want of Foot, or through a vain confidence of his own ſtrength, having ſtill an Army of <hi>120000.</hi> fighting men, he neglected theſe advantages.</p>
            <p>The Chriſtian Army, which conſiſted of between <hi>70.</hi> and <hi>80000.</hi> men, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancing towards this place, a great Body of Horſe and Dragoons was ſent on the 11th to ſeize the chief Paſſages and Avenues of the Wood, which the Army having afterward paſſed, they poſted themſelves in the evening at the entrance of the Wood, on the ſide towards the Enemy, and there being a hill at a ſmall diſtance from them, ſome Troops were ſent to ſecure it, and all things were diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed for the Battel the next day; the right Wing was given to the King of <hi>Poland,</hi> for that he had the moſt Horſe, and that the Countrey was on that ſide open; the left to the Elector of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> and the Duke of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> becauſe they were ſtrongest in Foot, and that it was an encloſed Countrey all along the <hi>Denube:</hi> and the main Body to the Elector of <hi>Saxony,</hi> and Prince <hi>Waldecke.</hi> The next morning by break of day, the Generals, according to appointment, met on the Hill before mentioned, to give the laſt Orders, and were no ſooner come thither, but a Body of about <hi>10000.</hi> Turks appeared, and advanced towards the Christians, whereupon a Battalion was ordered to put themſelves into a Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard that was on a Hill hard by, being ſupported by three other Battalions, which made the Turks ſtop, for not enduring the Fire of the ſaid Battalions, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all Horſe, and in a Ground where they could not well attack the Foot, they contented themſelves with making one Diſcharge, accompanied with a hideous noiſe, and ſo retired. Hereupon the King of <hi>Poland</hi> and the other Princes having obſerved the diſpoſition of the Enemy, drew the Army in three Lines, all cloſed without any Intervals, and Ordered them to march very ſlowly towards the Enemy, and to stand when the Turks came to Charge them, to keep themſelves very cloſe, and not to Fire till the Enemy had made their diſcharge, which was accordingly done. The Enemy advanced towards them with a horrible cry, as if they meant to break in upon them, hoping thereby to make them give w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> or to put them into diſorder, but perceiving that the Chriſtians ſtood firm, and expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them in a very cloſe order, they durſt not puſh any farther, but made a halt, and finding the Chriſtians did not ſtir, but stood expecting them, they made their diſcharge and wheeled off, upon which all the firſt Line of the Christians fired, and that done, the whole Army advanced with a ſlow pace, and ſo gained ground upon the Enemy, who returning, came up as before, the Christians thereupon made a halt, and expected them, and the Turks having made their Diſcharge, again retired, which they repeated ſeveral times without ever daring to break in upon the Chriſtians, who ſtill gained Ground, and drove the Turks before them like a flock of Sheep; Being come near the Enemies Camp, a Body of Foot and
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:178853:2"/>Dragoons was detached to attack their Cannon, which they made themſelves Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of without much Oppoſition, the Enemy having but a ſmall number of Foot to defend them, and even their Horſe made no great reſiſtance in any place, though on the ſide of the right Wing, they endeavoured to charge the Chriſtians in Flank, but the King of <hi>Poland</hi> miſtrusting it, cauſed part of the ſecond Line to advance, and make a Front on that ſide, and charging the Enemy in Perſon with the first Line, made them give way. During the hotteſt of the Battel, the Turks attack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Town, and preſſed the Beſieged ſo hard, that the Count <hi>De Staremberg</hi> was forced to ſend to the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> for aſſiſtance, with the help whereof, all the Turks that were in the Attack were cut in pieces. In concluſion, towards night the Enemy began to give way and to fly, the Chriſtians purſuing them beyond their Camp, and there they made a halt, the Souldiers being commanded upon pain of death not to ſtir out of their Ranks, and the whole Army remained all night in Battalia, as if the Enemy had been ſtill preſent. The next day the Camp was plundered, half of a Company going out at a time, while the other half continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in Arms, and when they returned, theſe went out in like manner. All the Enemies Baggage, Proviſions, Tents, <hi>50.</hi> pieces of Cannon, two Horſe-Tails, the <hi>Grand Seignior</hi>'s Standard, and the <hi>Viſiers</hi>'s own Horſe were taken, and moſt of their Foot were cut in pieces, which it's believed was not above <hi>12.</hi> or <hi>15000.</hi> they having loſt an incredible number during the Siege. This great Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory which was obtained at ſo cheap a rate, that the Chriſtians loſt not a <hi>1000.</hi> men, and very few Perſons of Note, (the Duke <hi>de Croy,</hi> and ſome others being wound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) must in great meaſure be attributed to the great Conduct and Bravery of the King of <hi>Poland,</hi> who engaged in Perſon among the thickeſt of the Enemy, having with him the Prince his eldeſt Son, but <hi>15.</hi> years old <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> who thus early ſignalized himſelf; the Electors of <hi>Bavaria</hi> and <hi>Saxony,</hi> the Duke of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> and Prince <hi>Waldecke,</hi> have likewiſe gained great Honour and Rep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>utation, much of the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of this great Day being due to them.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> Re-printed by the Heir of <hi>Andrew Anderſon,</hi> Printer to His moſt Sacred Majeſty. 1683.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
